Amay Kataria

646-761-5173 - <u>akataria@saic.edu</u> - <u>www.amaykataria.com</u> - www.github.com/eulphean

Amay Kataria (b. 1990) draws inspiration from phenomenology, culture, and natural observations and utilizes technology to intervene and initiate a dialog. His interests lie in repurposing and inventing electronic media in ways that stimulates the senses and expands the mind to offer profound insights into the implications - both positive and negative of techno culture. His work stems from building digital and physical systems and intersecting them with computer algorithms and computation to draw out the essence of such systems. By intersecting art, design, technology, and science, his artistic passion fuels by closely observing the new and upcoming technology with a critical outlook. From blockchain to kinetics, he develops sensorial aesthetic experiences that approaches Art & Technology Studies from a futuristic and fresh perspective. He is currently pursuing a MFA in Art and Technology Studies at SAIC and is expected to graduate in 2019.

EDUCATION

MFA, Art and Technology Studies, *Expected Graduation*, 2019 School of the Art Institute of Chicago

B.S., Computer Engineering, December 2012

Virginia Tech

Concentration in embedded systems, hardware-software design, data structures & algorithms, and interdisciplinary product design.

CGPA: 3.84, Rank: 6/126, Summa Cum Laude

<u>Honors & Awards:</u> Bernard Silverman, Byron M. & Helen S. Brumback, Gilbert L. and Lucille C. Seay, MR. and CP. Staley Memorial, Litton Industries, Benjamin F. Bock, James Milton Beattie Jr.

SKILLS

Languages

C++, C, Javascript, C#, Objective-C, PureData

Tools

OpenFrameworks, Processing, Git, Arduino, RaspberryPI, ReactXp, React, React-Native, Unity, AngularJS, EmberJS, Bootstrap

Design/Sound

Sketch, GIMP, Adobe Photoshop, Sonic Pi, Ableton Live, Logic

SELECTED EXHIBITIONS & AWARDS

2018

Nabi Art Center Residency, Seoul, Korea

Accepted resident for a 6 weeks residency program to develop an Art and Blockchain installation

Art-A-Hack Thoughtworks Residency, New York City, NY

Current resident in a 5-week residency on Climate Psychology and Climate Consciousness project.

Shapiro Research Level-Up Grant, Chicago, IL

Awarded a research grant to expand a sound installation project developed at School of the Art Institute of Chicago during Spring 2018 semester.

Ethereal Summit, New York City, NY

Exhibited work as a visiting artist for Art & Blockchain conference in New York.

Waveforms, Experimental Sound Studio, Chicago, IL

MFA Thesis Show, Sullivan Galleries, Chicago, IL

Small-Pop Hypothesis, collaboration with a 2nd year Sculpture student from SAIC.

Algomotion, SAIC, Chicago, IL

Art & Technology Studies exhibition

Save Lives Charity Event, Lincoln Hall, Chicago, IL

Art auction for charity

2017

Creative Coding Exhibition, SAIC, Chicago, IL

Art & Technology Studies exhibition

Answering Machine, SAIC, Chicago, IL

Art & Technology Studies exhibition for 1st year students

2016

Microsoft //oneweek Hackathon Science Fair, Seattle, WA

Exhibited Earth Lens

Startup Weekend with music vertical, Seattle, WA *Exhibited Magic Mic*

2015

Chapel of Meditation, SeaWeed Camp, Burning Man, Black Rock City, Nevada

2007

Future Cities 2050, Washington DC

After winning an all-India competition called Future Cities 2020, our team of 4 students were invited to United States to present our designs in the Future Cities 2050 competition in Washington DC.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant, School of the Art Institute of Chicago, 2017 - 2018

Interactive Art and Intro to Computer Vision and Machine Learning with professor Christopher Baker

Kinetics and Computer Control with professor Jacob Tonski.

Electronics and Kinetics Lab Assistant, School of the Art Institute of Chicago, 2017 - 2018

Software Engineer, Skype for Consumers, Microsoft, 2014 - 2017

Seattle, WA

- Worked across CoreUI, Messaging, and Fundamental squads to develop high-impact features for the next-gen Skype client shipped on iOS and Android platforms in June, 2017.
- Contributed to ReactXp, an open-source platform based on React and React-Native developed by Microsoft for cross-platform application development using Javascript.
- Developed distributed scalable backend applications like Skype's feedback service and machine learning driven Skype bots. Integrated Microsoft's bot infrastructure into next-gen Skype client's user interface.
- Architected and developed the complete Accessibility platform for next-generation Skype on ReactXP and collaborated with all the Skype team to make the application accessible.

Software Engineer, Skype for Business, Microsoft, 2014

Seattle, WA

Shipped a companion mobile web app for iOS, Android, and Windows Phone, which communicated with an embedded hardware device via bluetooth to make scheduling and attending Skype meetings portable.

Software Engineer, Windows Hyper-V, Microsoft, 2013 Seattle, WA Developed next-gen test tools for Virtual Machine creation and deployment in Hyper-V in C#.

Software Engineering Intern, Qualcomm, May 2012 - August 2012 San Diego, California Developed Object-Oriented C++ test code for testing Qualcomm's proprietary messaging interface between modem and application processors on Windows phone.

Systems Solutions Engineering Intern, Harris Corporation, Spring 2010 Lynchburg, VA

Implemented Land Mobile Radio systems by utilizing company proprietary software called RAPTR for Public Safety Communication Networks in United States states and counties.